<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>

<title>Daniel Rashevsky</title>
<link>https://drashevsky.github.io</link>
<description>Daniel Rashevsky's personal website.</description>
<atom:link href="https://drashevsky.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
     <title>Half-Baked Ideas - Digital Hawala</title>
     <link>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/DigitalHawala.html</link>
     <guid>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/DigitalHawala.html</guid>
     <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawala">Hawala</a> is an informal money transmission system popular in the Middle East, Africa, and India. At its most basic, it relies on two reputable brokers establishing ties with each other, and agreeing to deliver their own money to recipients upon request. A sender can then ask one broker to send money to somebody far away by depositing money, getting the broker to ask their counterparty broker to discharge their own funds, and then adding the deposited funds to the counterparty broker&#39;s &quot;balance&quot;. All for a fee.</p>
<p>I propose <strong>digital hawala</strong> - a distributed reputation sharing and telegraphic balance transfer system. Unlike cryptocurrency, this system is <strong>built around trust</strong>, rather than trying to <strong>eliminate all trust</strong>. At the end of the day, all money is given value by people <strong>choosing</strong> to value it. People choose to value certain kinds of money and transact with it based on faith that they will be able to successfully obtain goods and services. The financial system relies on centralization because trust is the bedrock of any successful transaction, and trusted brokers attract more people willing to transact with them. Eliminating all trust and implementing a completely adversarial system defeats the whole point of finance. This is seen in the development of centralized crypto exchanges, and the hard consequences of not perfectly securing crypto / smart contracts. However, this does not mean the financial system can&#39;t take advantage of decentralization or web technologies.</p>
<p>Here is one example of how digital hawala can work:</p>
<ul>
<li>Digital hawala operates as a distributed trust network [0], where every node has:<ul>
<li>Public/private key pair</li>
<li>A ledger of trust scores on other nodes ranging from 0 to 1<ul>
<li>0 - cannot be trusted</li>
<li>1 - completes all network actions/transactions faithfully (even if they are illegal)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>&quot;Balances&quot; open with other nodes</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The less other nodes judge your trust score to be, the less inclined they will be to increase your balances with them / deliver cash on your behalf</li>
<li>To transfer some <em>part of a balance</em>, a node contacts a counterparty node that it mutually trusts and has a balance with, and requests <em>part of it</em> to be delivered to the destination in cash</li>
<li>These transactions can be chained trusted node to trusted node if the source and destination nodes don&#39;t directly trust each other, which is more likely as geographic distance increases</li>
<li>Every node starts with a trust score of 0 and infinitely low spend limits, limiting it to increasing its balances / trust score with other nodes by:<ul>
<li>Sending the counterparty nodes real dollars</li>
<li>Sending real dollars to recipients on behalf of the counterparty nodes to build up balances with them</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Nodes earn trust by<ul>
<li>Completing successful transactions</li>
<li>Honestly reporting trust scores</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>This incentivizes other nodes to &quot;vouch&quot; for them. Trust is calculated by asking other trusted nodes for their opinions of the target node</li>
<li>System is built in a way to incentivize:<ul>
<li>Completing honest transactions (double spending, failing to complete transactions, disputes, etc. lowers trust score)</li>
<li>Honestly reporting trust score (if a node lies about another node&#39;s trust score, this discrepancy w/ other reports causes requesting nodes to penalize it)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>The decentralized nature of this system, as well as incentives that drive nodes to honestly play by the rules / complete transactions, makes it efficient and resilient.</p>
<p>[0] <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_of_trust">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_of_trust</a></p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
     <title>Renovating the Ivory Tower</title>
     <link>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/IvoryTower.html</link>
     <guid>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/IvoryTower.html</guid>
     <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>Let&#39;s be honest. Academia these days is floundering. In the STEM world, real scientific advances are being stifled by the replication crisis, toxic environments within labs, PHD burnout, and the politics of grant writing. Research into breakthroughs such as immunotherapy and RNA vaccines ends up being overlooked where it could otherwise have impacted millions of lives.</p>
<p>The humanities front, meanwhile, is plagued with issues such as the lack of empirical and quantitative research, erosion of neutrality, lousy standards on research quality, and a single-minded adherence to ideology. They stifle research into everything that&#39;s off the party line, leaving us with a poorer understanding of our society and culture.</p>
<p>From both sides, the ivory tower is caved in by extreme politicization, censorship, the silencing of minority views, the tenure caste system, authoritarian and bloated administrations, grade inflation, credentialism, and entrenched discrimination that keeps college presidents occupied with lawsuits, Department of Education investigations, and Congressional hearings.</p>
<p>All these problems are symptoms of a failing elitist system that gatekeeps access to ideas, inquiry, and research. Thus, America cannot solely rely on academia in order to preserve its innovative edge.</p>
<p>I propose the creation of a new kind of organization - a nonprofit research studio - and a lean research governance system to shepherd it. These two new constructs will complement the existing academic system, while focusing on academic freedom and supplying solutions tailored for commercialization or remixing into broader culture. These organizations will be run more like startups than the traditional top-down English department or biochemistry lab. This means that anybody within them is empowered to propose ideas and drive research, with continuous metrics and an agile process serving as the heartbeat of the organization. Volumes have been written on how to organize a lean startup to reach product market fit and scale. Research studios can apply a similar concept.</p>
<p>But how will these research studios be funded, incentivized to produce quality research in interesting/societally important directions, and vetted? This is where the lean governance system comes in. Instead of the closed and heavily bureaucratic structure of a university, the lean governance system is an open system. This means anybody can start a research studio (with some funding caveats). </p>
<p>Grants are the lifeblood of research right now, and the federal government pours billions into the old ivory tower hierarchy. This fundamentally misaligns incentives to promote incremental, &quot;safe&quot;, fundable advances, with no reward for taking on risky research or overlooked directions. To stand up our studios, some of this funding should be diverted to provide them with an initial cash injection. To prevent a complete run on government money, this amount will be capped and limited to those with 4 years of post-secondary education or equivalent experience. And now the best part. Research studios will be permitted to solicit outside funding and commercialize their research to their hearts content. This means licensing patents, publishing books, banding together to publish research journals, forming partnerships with private / political / non-profit orgs, etc. The market decides which ideas are winners.</p>
<p>To establish some ground rules and prevent total havoc in this new research system, the lean governance system will have a democratic leadership elected by the research studios themselves, which can form into Westminster-style coalitions that would replace the siloed departments in the old ivory tower. This leadership will set standards and regulations for research studios, determine which core fields get additional funding, monitor research journals, etc. One of the benefits of the old academic system was peer review. Rigorous scientific and literary standards will be established that are completely neutral and objective in evaluating research quality.</p>
<p>What is the end result of all of this work? No system is perfect, but I believe that by creating a space where anybody can engage in a battle of ideas against other individuals and groups, the best ideas will rise to the top. Instead of being shut down and relegated to obscurity, one can take a risk on a risky research direction and hit the jackpot. Innovation will inevitably be squeezed out as different research studios jockey for influence, whether that is in making money, fundraising, collaborating with other research studios, or getting into coalitions to influence governance. This will produce a Darwinian effect with results that will be highly competitive with the old academia system, and relevant to society at large. I hope we can see more foundational reforms to America&#39;s innovation ecosystem in the future. This is how we as a country will keep our edge in a rapidly changing world.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
     <title>The LLM Hype Bubble, and What Comes Next</title>
     <link>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/LLMHypeBubble.html</link>
     <guid>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/LLMHypeBubble.html</guid>
     <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>Nobody disputes the usefulness of large language models. LLMs can do &quot;intellectual grunt work&quot;, such as suggesting a well-placed word for an essay or filling in the background of an artwork. This is a huge value add and breakthrough because it cuts the effort needed to produce a creative work in half, even if it makes mistakes (hallucinations).</p>
<p>The problem is, LLMs are <strong>generative</strong>, not <strong>creative</strong>. They cannot think <strong>originally</strong>, only relying on situations they&#39;ve already seen to navigate the world. They struggle when they encounter a new or unexpected scenario. This is because they possess no logical/intuitive understanding of it, whether they need to completing the structure of a paper or determine how to architect a complex service keeping track of weeds that need to be zapped with lasers. Since the world is infinitely complex, the point of any creative process is responding to new situations with novel and original thinking.</p>
<p>If I read 100 papers on the central message of Shakespeare&#39;s Macbeth, I can probably plagiarize a good paper on the subject. But if I try to write an analysis on why Shakespeare used iambic pentameter and how it relates to British poetry development in the late 16th century by reading those same 100 papers, I will flounder.</p>
<p>Eventually, all the &quot;intellectual grunt work&quot; use cases will run out, <strong>which is when I believe the LLM hype bubble will burst.</strong> But will the computing field have peaked after this event? If not, what will become the next big computer breakthrough?</p>
<p>To answer that question, we have to go back to the fundamentals of what a computer is. Computers are special in that they are machines developed not to help the human body solve physical problems, but to help the human brain solve cognitive ones. From rudimentary slide rulers to the first mainframe to personal computers, the computing field has expanded by iteratively automating parts of the human thought process. Therefore, the next big computing advancement lies in a part of this thought process that hasn&#39;t been automated yet - which is <strong>getting computers to intuitively understand the physical and logical world around them</strong>.</p>
<p>This is something our brains do continuously throughout the day, utilizing a neural network to &quot;understand&quot; certain electrical signals. For example, signals fired by optic nerves are interpreted a &quot;picture&quot;. If you cover your eyes for months or wear mirrors that flip your vision upside down, your brain forgets how to see or learns to see upside down.  </p>
<p>However, even humans don&#39;t get turnkey awareness on day 1. Human brains are born with the necessary &quot;hardware&quot;, sensory capabilities, and instincts, but they have to grow their brain&#39;s &quot;logic and intuition&quot; engine to process the inputs into a practical and emotional understanding of the world around them. Babies take time to develop vision, attention span, and logic. Infants take tens of examples to learn what a &quot;dog&quot; is and why it is different from a &quot;cat&quot;. A toddler needs to be taught to properly process their rage without throwing a temper tantrum. This process does not fully finish until age 25.</p>
<p>I am excited about systems that help computers understand logic, like program synthesis/verification systems, solvers, expert systems, as well as real world phenomena, like computer vision algorithms and signal processors. This list is not all-encompassing. However, advances from these kinds of systems will advance the computing field into finally creating machines with that logical and intuitive understanding of their surroundings.</p>]]></description>
</item>
<item>
     <title>The Second Brain (Information Overload) Problem</title>
     <link>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/SecondBrain.html</link>
     <guid>https://drashevsky.github.io/posts/SecondBrain.html</guid>
     <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>Smart people and entrepreneurs need to consume, generate, and process massive amounts of information these days to maximize their success in the knowledge economy. These energetic people are bursting at the seams with thoughts, ideas, commentary, newly learned subjects, and more. It becomes hard to stay on top of things due to <strong>information overload</strong>: the exponentially rising difficulty and time commitment of organizing large amounts of diverse information across different services/platforms.</p>
<h2 id="problems-of-generic-note-apps">Problems of generic note apps</h2>
<p>Note apps are limited in scope, used for narrow topics like class notes or shopping lists where a linear set of similar sized items, or multiple linear sets behind tags/folders allows for quick scrolling and retrieval. When there are multiple topics or information comes in different sizes a note app quickly becomes cluttered and unorganized, exponentially increasing the time needed to organize &amp; retrieve it.</p>
<h2 id="user-research-questions">User Research Questions</h2>
<ul>
<li>   <em>What problems with information overload and organizing information do entrepreneurs and knowledge workers have have?</em></li>
<li>   <em>Can we help them with a knowledge base (second brain)?</em></li>
</ul>
<h1 id="description-of-market">Description of Market</h1>
<p><strong>Initial Demographic</strong>: entrepreneurs and highly productive knowledge workers facing information overload</p>
<p><strong>Nature of Information Overload</strong>: a constant stream of “knowledge items” of various sizes that are impossible to lump into one category, being exponentially more difficult/time-consuming to organize</p>
<h2 id="whats-already-out-there">What’s already out there:</h2>
<ul>
<li>   <strong>Obsidian, Roam Research, Athens Research, Notion</strong>, Zotero, Dendron, generic notes apps like OneNote and Evernote, Pocket, RSS readers, subscriptions, inboxes, Anki/Remnote/Mochi, and Workflowy/Dynalist.</li>
<li>   All solve related/overlapping problems related to a second brain, or are hard to learn and maintain.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="memai-and-ideaflow-remarks">Mem.ai and Ideaflow: Remarks</h2>
<p><a href="https://mem.ai">Mem.ai</a> is a newer app that is the closest yet to reflecting what&#39;s described in this write-up. It is rapidly developing and could really shake things up. <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/04/06/note-taking-app-mem-raises-5-6-million-from-andreessen-horowitz/">Article talking about A16Z funding for Mem.ai</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.ideaflow.io/">Ideaflow</a>: Also has an approach similar to this write-up&#39;s, but has not been very impressive technically</p>
<h2 id="the-state-of-the-market-today">The State of the Market Today</h2>
<p>Notes &amp; knowledge apps: literally the most generic and deceptively difficult market to enter. Right now, changes including the transition to the knowledge economy, advances in neuroscience and information management, and remote working are driving a whole host of new market entrants of all shapes and sizes. The ground is churning with hypercompetition. However, as one HN user put it:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Things like Roam represent a very tiny fragment of a much larger puzzle that&#39;s existed for years prior to their existence. From a 
theoretical perspective, they are only novel insofar as they exist as concrete products today.
Sometimes it&#39;s healthy when spaces heavily fragment due to hypercompetiton. It allows products with strong technical and theoretical 
groundwork to show up later and render the entire space effectively obsolete.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I think we are still looking for that &quot;perfect&quot; product.</p>
<h1 id="potential-solution-requirements-the-metabase">Potential Solution Requirements: The Metabase</h1>
<p>A new type of knowledge base called a <strong>Metabase</strong>, due to the way it would integrate the Internet/computing so tightly with the physical world it can be classified as a <em>Metaverse application</em>. </p>
<p><strong>Tagline</strong>: Revolutionize the human brain</p>
<p><strong>Explain Like I&#39;m Five</strong>: It&#39;s a second brain 1 billion times more powerful than yours! Like TikTok for your notes</p>
<p><strong>Breakout Product Idea</strong>: idea/brainstorm categorizer (very related)</p>
<p><em>Don&#39;t show favoritism towards any one technical solution, architecture, or paradigm</em> - The target demographic and their needs/problems should be extensively researched first, pound the dirt and talk to dozens of them. Then, technical solutions can be developed to meet those needs. </p>
<p>Solution should be built around specifics of the human brain’s consciousness and information processing, including:</p>
<ul>
<li>   The syllogism loop (come up with simple facts, synthesize into more complex conclusions)</li>
<li>   Subconscious information processing (go to bed with problem, wake up with solution) </li>
<li>   Memory techniques like spaced repetition (Anki) and memory palace</li>
<li>   Systemic thinking/analysis: being able to deconstruct complex things into simpler pieces
Most likely an AI needs to be trained around this, I highly doubt this kind of advanced learning system can be built without a neural network.</li>
<li>Connections between loosely related information</li>
<li>Etc...</li>
</ul>
<p>The solution should have <strong>zero</strong> learning curve! You open it, and it makes sense instantly!</p>
<p><strong>Needed specialists to build solution</strong>: Neuroscientists, UX researchers, algorithm designers, information architects</p>
<h1 id="example-metabase-solution">Example Metabase Solution</h1>
<p>A powerful knowledge base system where you just throw things at it and it organizes them for you with no effort on your part. This prevents knowledge from piling up, and increases knowledge flow into the system. </p>
<h2 id="auto-organization-of-knowledge">Auto-Organization of Knowledge</h2>
<p>You don&#39;t organize it personally, an AI trained on previous content and organized on neuroscience principles can process or dream about your knowledge and place it right where it needs to be, similar to how TikTok automatically knows what kinds of videos you like. No more need for thinking about your knowledge: <strong>the machine is the information architect</strong>. No more need for choosing between graphs, linear lists, infinite trees, combinations of folders and tags, etc.</p>
<h2 id="a-potential-architecture">A Potential Architecture</h2>
<ul>
<li>Knowledge bases can be evaluated using this paradigm: Thoughtless Input -&gt; Magic Sorting Storage -&gt; Instant Output. </li>
<li><em>Thoughtless Input</em>: multiple synced interfaces connecting to storage system, allow thoughtless input by typing directly into it/direct inclusion of formats of information like links. Can include info in part of knowledge base, or let the system find where to put it for you. </li>
<li><em>Magic Sorting Storage</em>: AI system, organized similar to how TikTok finds your interests. Goal is to prevent knowledge from piling up in any one place, reduce exponential difficulty/time commitment of organizing large amounts of knowledge, and integrate multiple kinds of knowledge, like links and notes. infinite space. Using graphs maybe (<em>internally</em>)?</li>
<li><em>Instant Output</em>: easy search function or curated sorting system should let taking knowledge out of system and sharing it happen instantly</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="notes-on-business-strategy-and-product-specifics">Notes on Business Strategy and Product Specifics</h2>
<ul>
<li>Make an engine with multiple synced interfaces such as mobile apps, browser extensions, desktop apps. etc to capture market share. </li>
<li>Provide enterprise services geared to organizational  knowledge (connect the minds of large amounts of people together into one readable collective base, plus private bases for individual). </li>
<li>Sharing and cross-platform allows for network effects. Free for individuals to capture them. </li>
<li>The marketing can be through channels such as HN, ProductHunt, etc, but the goal is that the product is so effective that people literally can&#39;t live without it, similar to how TikTok is extremely addicting</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="a-parting-word">A Parting Word</h1>
<p>In the United States, the transition to a full-blown knowledge economy has been in the works for years, with much tumult and social chaos as data reigns and physical jobs are automated away. To drive the breathtaking pace of innovation characterizing the last 100 years, the knowledge economy demands <strong>more and more human brainpower, now</strong>.</p>
<p>Our brains are already reaching the <strong>information overload barrier</strong>, beyond which only machines will be able to help us venture. I won&#39;t speak to the psychological and social effects of this, only that as a builder I know there is only one direction in which we can keep growing. While 100% brainpower like in the 2014 film &#39;Lucy&#39; or 2011 film &#39;Limitless&#39; is impossible, the human potential described by them is already in all of us. It just needs to be amplified to meet today&#39;s demands. A second brain or metabase&#39;s incalculable productivity gains would change humanity as a whole forever. </p>
<p>In the future with the development of BCI technology, we may see the concepts integrated, in effect reaching this 100% brainpower threshold. 
<strong>Language would cease being a bottleneck</strong>, with direct brain-to-brain &amp; brain-to-computer communication minimizing the need for us to use sound and writing to convey our thoughts and build knowledge. If we were to have &#39;benevolent AI masters&#39;, I feel like they would be humans augmented with second brains, maximizing the full potential of AI while keeping the human gifts of sentience and creativity.</p>
<h1 id="some-references">Some References</h1>
<h2 id="existing-methods-and-ideas">Existing Methods and Ideas</h2>
<p><a href="https://fortelabs.co/blog/basboverview/">https://fortelabs.co/blog/basboverview/</a>: Very well known and foundational course on second brain, super intensive</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_knowledge_management</a>: overview of the new field developing around managing second brains and information overload</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memex">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Memex</a>: very similar idea but its 80 years out of date</p>
<p><a href="https://www.bytesized.xyz/tools-for-thought/">https://www.bytesized.xyz/tools-for-thought/</a>: Andy Matuschak&#39;s brilliant thesis on second brain tools</p>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zettelkasten</a></p>
<h2 id="second-brain-blogvlogverse">Second Brain Blog/Vlogverse</h2>
<p><a href="https://daltonmabery.medium.com/what-apps-i-use-to-build-my-second-brain-5f5602dfeb3e">https://daltonmabery.medium.com/what-apps-i-use-to-build-my-second-brain-5f5602dfeb3e</a></p>
<p><a href="https://uxdesign.cc/building-a-second-brain-for-product-management-8a05cc4c5e4e">https://uxdesign.cc/building-a-second-brain-for-product-management-8a05cc4c5e4e</a></p>
<p><a href="https://medium.com/@elizabethmjoneswrites/im-building-a-second-brain-here-s-why-you-should-too-3ed777495689">https://medium.com/@elizabethmjoneswrites/im-building-a-second-brain-here-s-why-you-should-too-3ed777495689</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTI6Mxu3YiI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RTI6Mxu3YiI</a></p>
<h2 id="more-on-neuroscience-and-productivity">More on Neuroscience and Productivity</h2>
<p><a href="https://nesslabs.com/">https://nesslabs.com/</a></p>]]></description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
